<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The result of a dialogue concerning the middle-state of souls. Wherein is asserted, the ancient doctrine of their relief, obtainable by prayers, alms, &amp;c. before the day of judgment. / By F.D. professor of divinity.</title>
            <author>Franciscus a Sancta Clara, 1598-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D355A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175909</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52212011</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52212011</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175639</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175639)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2744:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The result of a dialogue concerning the middle-state of souls. Wherein is asserted, the ancient doctrine of their relief, obtainable by prayers, alms, &amp;c. before the day of judgment. / By F.D. professor of divinity.</title>
                  <author>Franciscus a Sancta Clara, 1598-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication supplied by Wing.</note>
                  <note>In ms. on p. [1]: Lib. Thos. Barlow ... Oct. 12. 1660.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Intermediate state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayers for the dead --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175639:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175639:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RESULT OF A DIALOGVE concerning the MIDLE-STATE of SOULS.</p>
            <p>Wherein is aſſerted The Ancient Doctrine of their Relief, obtainable by Prayers, Alms, &amp;c. before the Day of Judgment.</p>
            <p>By <hi>F. D.</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>PARIS, Permiſſu Superiorum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:175639:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175639:2"/>
            <head>For the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and Learned, <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Warder, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The <hi>Mecoenas</hi> of all Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Vertue.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SOme <hi>Ariſtopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> removing the controverſy of the <hi>Midle-ſtate of Soules</hi> out of the Schools, and improvid ently thrust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it (in Engliſh) into
<pb facs="tcp:175639:3"/>the hands of Ladies, whoſe <hi>curioſity</hi> is not alwayes proportioned to their <hi>capacity,</hi> hath been inſtrumentall of great Scandall. Hence upon intreaty of ſuch, who may command, I interpoſed, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to clear the ſtate of the Question, as I thought, without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, it might import; this occaſioned a reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procation of Epistles, wherein I would gladly
<pb facs="tcp:175639:3"/>prevent all miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, as alſo in the <hi>Synopſis</hi> of our Tenets, which I formerly gave in ſuch matters, which were eſteemed proper for the times.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reſult</hi> I preſent to your Lordſhips most judicious view, alſo to your noble Patronage. If it conduce to any good, I ſhall be ſure of the guerdon I hope for. Your Lordſhips heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary goodneſſe will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb facs="tcp:175639:4"/>my boldneſſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by your known Vertue, and great love of Truth, who ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly ſubſcribe, what by many titles, my duty obligeth me to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt devoted ſervant in all duty, <hi>F. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:175639:4"/>
            <head>A Table of the Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHap. 1. <hi>Relief in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is the Doctrine of holy Church</hi> 1</item>
               <item>Chap. 2. <hi>It is not matter of Opinion</hi> 11</item>
               <item>Chap. 3. <hi>Why the Reſurrection is inculcated</hi> 15</item>
               <item>Chap. 4. <hi>The ſenſes of Greek and Latine Liturgies and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> 24</item>
               <item>Cha. 5. <hi>Traditions alone cannot prove faith in all Articles</hi> 45</item>
               <item>Chap. 6. <hi>Charity conſiſts with Purgatory. The various ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Charity. Wherein conſists the chiefe penalty of Purgatory?</hi> 48</item>
               <item>Chap. 7. <hi>How a ſoul, according to others, can change? Of the horror of Doomſday. Whether it is to be prayed for?</hi> 67</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:175639:5"/>
               <item>Chap. 8. <hi>Whether a ſoul can be changed by God, and how, in Purgatory? The true ſtate of the controverſie explicated</hi> 89</item>
               <item>Chap. 9. <hi>The ſtate of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion further explicated. The difference betwixt an inſtant of time, and aeviternity declared. The reſolution of the Queſtion fully given, as to change of ſouls</hi> 99</item>
               <item>Chap. 10. <hi>Scriptures and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions muſt be obeyed. How one can ſatisfie for another? Whether, and how, other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues beſides charity, avail to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven?</hi> 117</item>
               <item>Chap. 11. <hi>How corporal afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can ſatisfie for ſins. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a probable Opinion may be followed</hi> 127</item>
               <item>Chap. 12. <hi>The deſigne of the Treatiſe</hi> 140</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175639:5"/>
            <head>The Reſult of a DIALOGVE concerning the MIDLE-STATE of SOULES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Relief in Purgatory is the Doctrine of holy Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN our laſt <hi>Epiſtolary Conference</hi> concerning the ſenſe of the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175639:6"/>Councel</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> and of <hi>Pope Benedict</hi> the eleventh, his <hi>Bul,</hi> againſt thoſe who hold, that <hi>none went to Heaven till the day of Judgement;</hi> you much inſiſted, that neither of them defined a Redemption out of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> before the great day. The Greeks there called it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It muſt be confeſs'd, that their principall deſign was the condemnation of <hi>Joh.</hi> 22. his error, which though he recanted, yet to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any reſuſcitation of it, it was judged neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conciliarly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175639:6"/>it. In diſcuſſing, or rather explicating the latitude of this, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to particulars, <hi>Who</hi> and <hi>When</hi> each ſort went to Heaven, either at, or after their deaths, according to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conditions; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in delivered their ſence of this, as being in part involved in the former. So that it was a Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary Declaration of the Churches Doctrine, as to this: that is, of the whole Chriſtian World, as all prior or poſterior Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, not violented (for it is eaſie to miſ-apply,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175639:7"/>and even elude the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with voluntary gloſſes out of <hi>Chamier,</hi> and other ſuch like bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Authors) and the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal tradition orally delivered, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, declare.</p>
               <p>See in S. <hi>John Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> almoſt all the <hi>Greek Fathers,</hi> even incluſively, from great <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> to himſelfe, and ſome of the Latines alſo are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in him, who all aſſert this, and ſay, that from our Lords Diſciples it deſcended, &amp; obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, and through the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175639:7"/>whole Church of God with great profit to the dead. And that you may clearly by one under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the received inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the reſt, ſee there the ſtory of great <hi>Macarius,</hi> who had from God this Anſwer: <hi>Quo tempore,</hi> inquit, <hi>mortuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſa preces offers, tum ſane nonnullius ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii ſenſu afficimur.</hi> Thus a dead man's ſkull an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him. We muſt not then expect <hi>Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> for an anſwer of our Prayers. Nay, S. <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcen</hi> ſaith, it is a <hi>new, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd</hi> doctrine, ſuggeſted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175639:8"/>by the Devil, <hi>Pia omnia opera, quae mortem ſequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nullam omnino defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis utilitatem afferre:</hi> &amp; truly his ingenuous ſenſe is, that to deny any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by them before the day of Judgment to the dead, deſcends from the Devil. I refer you to all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in him; whence you will ſee how they are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lented for the contrary by others.</p>
               <p>It is a moſt unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able rule in this matter, as to the affirmative, though <hi>a posteriori</hi> (as we ſpeak) amongſt all probable Doctors, who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175639:8"/>have the honour to have their memories celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Faſts of the Schools, <hi>That whatſoever is declared in a Generall Councel, which is received, or not</hi> impunè <hi>reſiſted by Catholique Doctors of the age wherein it is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is by all Christians to he admitted in the ſame degree in which it is there declared.</hi> Which Rule comes home to all points by Sectaries now contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, as I have parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularized in my <hi>Syſtem:</hi> and eſpecially compels us to an acceptance of this preſent <hi>Article,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175639:9"/>to the ſame place it obtained in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> and the age wherein it was cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated. The firſt I have ſpecified as far as this place permits. The later is evident by all Writers then, and ever ſince, in the <hi>Church:</hi> though <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Epheſius,</hi> an eminent Greek Schiſmatique, if not rather an Heretique, who was preſent in the Councel, recalcitrated in vain againſt it, in ſome particulars, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this at all; which ſtill confirmes us in it. <hi>Gennadius,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:175639:9"/>ſaith, this Councel was, <hi>ubique promulgatum, &amp; ab omnibus gentibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum:</hi> only <hi>vulgares quidam homines, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docti</hi> did contradict. He adds, if any capable of reaſon reſiſted, it was pravity of mind, not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning but fooliſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and vain glory, which moved it. Here he glances at <hi>Marck,</hi> and others deceived by him. All this faithfully appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, irrefragably declares our obligation to accept this truth accordingly.</p>
               <p>And moreover as to us in particular, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175639:10"/>reſiſtance made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this new Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by all at the very firſt dawning of it in our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulary Hemiſphere, as being a novilty oppoſite to what all from their infancies had learned, convinces the ſame. Nay Mr. <hi>Whites Sonus Bucci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae</hi> will inferre ſo much, and alone ſuffice accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to him, to prove matters even of Faith. But let us go further: if every perſon from hence to <hi>Cades</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175639:10"/>thence to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> through both Churches were asked, whether in their prayers for the dead, they do not hope to help them to Heaven before the laſt day? eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one would aſſert it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>It is not matter of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THerefore moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the hope of preſent eaſing them, was not grounded on matter of Opinion, which intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſically involves actuall fear, or doubt, of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175639:11"/>truth, elſe they would have praied faintly: but it is a traditionary do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and under that notion, by all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Hence we never read in Scriptures, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, or Fathers, any one clear aſſertion (as ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appears in thoſe which are moſt urged) That <hi>all thoſe that go to Purgatory muſt be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily detained there, without any relief, till the day of judgement;</hi> which ſure were impoſſible, if there had been any fluctuation in it, or if they had been of that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175639:11"/>as ſome gently perſwade us.</p>
               <p>That ſome things have been delivered to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Church, which could never obtain more authority then opinion, I have made evident in my <hi>Syſtem,</hi> even in grave Subjects of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this was not: but how to diſtinguiſh ſuch from doctrines of a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er nature, in caſe Holy Church did not conveigh clearly their qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with them, as in ſome caſes, evidently it did and in others it did not, as there I give inſtances;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175639:12"/>then the onely way is to return to <hi>general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,</hi> that they according to their office may <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitione facta,</hi> after the example of the Apoſtles, <hi>juridically</hi> appoint to each their ſeats, where all muſt <hi>acquieſce,</hi> as here was done conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all antiquity, as I have declared, and ſhall more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:175639:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Why the reſurrection is inculcated.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> indeed, our B. <hi>Lord,</hi> and eſpecially, B. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſince them, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church, and Fathers, moſt preſſingly incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the truth of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reſurrection, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>baſis</hi> of our hope, the motive of piety, and good works; all which would be adjudged fruitleſs by the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of men, if it were not for this: though even <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:175639:13"/>who with the reſt of his friends of <hi>Athens</hi> would have laughed to have heard Saint <hi>Paul</hi> Preach, and aſſert it; yet they would judge vertue to carry and bring with it a preſent reward, for which it ſhould be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced: but our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations are infinitely higher by our believed, and hoped for reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and therefore it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies produced propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate effects in Gods holy Martyrs, and Saints, eſpecially in thoſe firſt times, as the courſe of Gods providence requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175639:13"/>and therefore there was a neceſſity effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſettle this radical doctrine, as alſo of the laſt judgement to incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a juſt fear, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did. This other of relief of ſouls, in, and out of Purgatory, being of far leſs concernment, as to the generality of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and being as it were a particular of it, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alternate to it, needed not ſo ſtrong &amp; frequent inculcation, though holy Church did not take it up upon vulgar and light hear-ſayes, but with, and by the Apoſtles Praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175639:14"/>which, according to S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Rule, are ſufficiently proved by the Churches Doctrine, and practice. The holy Scriptures themſelves, as interpreted by antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alſo declare it, which are obviouſly knowne: Neither do the Texts, though brought with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, touch the contrary; nor were ever ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted. Some miſtake al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ariſeth in this buſineſs, from not obſerving, that holy Scriptures, and from thence holy Church, and the Fathers frequently underſtand by Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175639:14"/>even the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſouls to Heaven without the bodies, and therefore S. <hi>Aug.</hi> calleth the later of ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the <hi>perfect</hi> reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as condiſtinct from the former, in his <hi>care of the dead, c.</hi> 6. But here we treat of the Churches practice and doctrine; which are cleare even amongſt the Greekes as well as Latines: You know, that according to Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>White,</hi> (whoſe authority cannot be denied by you) the publique practice, or oral conveyance, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175639:15"/>univerſal Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſequently Chriſtian Truths.</p>
               <p>Therefore when I look upon the anxious ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, with which now, and in all former ages, good Chriſtians, Greeks and Latines, have proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted their friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed with their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Alms-deeds, which all Chriſtian Monuments declare: methinkes it were ſtrange now at length to have all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into a cold Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or Prayer for Doomſday: wherin their particular Allies are no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175639:15"/>more concerned, than all others: &amp; ſo all the pious indeavours of friends are of no effect, as relating to what they intended in order to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but might as well be contracted into a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Prayer for all the dead, againſt not onely orall tradition, but the manifeſt writings of the moſt ancient and learned in the bulke of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient teſtimony for all the reſt, in his Treatiſe of this ſubject, ſtiled by him, <hi>A care of the dead,</hi> where he ſuppoſeth it to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:175639:16"/>be the common ſenſe of the whole Catholique Church, that particular perſons dead, <hi>who have acquired merit in their life time, by which ſuch things may be rendred profitable after death, do receive benefit by what is done for them religiouſly after their deceaſe:</hi> and he ſpeaks cleane through the whole Book of actual benefit, profit, help, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, availment, and reſt to be procured for the ſouls. And leſt we ſhould gloſſe it for the ſoules in their reunion with their bodies, he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175639:16"/>frequently ſpeakes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctively of the ſoule as ſeparated from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or as it is when the <hi>body is dead;</hi> and he ſaith, that then it <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſuccour:</hi> which, as he ſhews, and I have ſaid, was the practice of all Churches in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Liturgies. I do not eſteem it conſtancy, but obſtinacy, to intort antiquity to our ſenſe gainſt their own.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:175639:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The ſences of Greek, and Latine Lyturgies and Fathers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMongſt the Greeks, I obſerve in their Liturgies, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they pray with <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, de Monogamia,</hi> that the dead may have <hi>refrigerium,</hi> that is, ſome eaſe, as S. <hi>Greg. Nazian.</hi> his Liturgie p. 34, in the Rubrick. Other times they pray, that they may be put into a place of light ſommeſs, where ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is baniſht and groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175639:17"/>&amp;c. as in S. <hi>Baſils</hi> Liturgie. Sometimes that they may reſt in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> boſome, as in S. <hi>James</hi> his Liturgie. All theſe intimate a change, a preſent relief, though not alwayes a releaſe, as the ſtile evidently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports: which deſtroyes your very ground; for you teach that no pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers can relieve, or change them till Doomes-day. S. <hi>James</hi> in his Lyturgie prayes, that God would cauſe the ſouls to reſt with the Saints. You ſay, he meanes, that they may not reſt, or have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175639:18"/>eaſe, or lightſomneſs, &amp;c. till after the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly pray for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſins, as in S. <hi>Baſils,</hi> and the reſt; this is not for the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: and finally they pray for all, who died in communion of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and for particular perſons recommended to the Prieſt, in each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, exactly agreeing with the Roman Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieremias,</hi> their <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch,</hi> followes them, and the ſenſe of both Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es frequently appears to be, that by their prayers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175639:18"/>they may obtain preſent eaſe, <hi>ut a poenis releven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Councel of Florence</hi> in the decree in <hi>Gennadius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was a queſtion amongſt ſome of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <hi>whether ſouls (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Martyrs) had a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſight of God before the laſt day:</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of it I have exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in my <hi>Syſtem.</hi> Hence ſome ſpoke warily, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the full releaſe out of Purgatory; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves a going to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but all agreed as to our preſent eaſe, and relief by Prayers, Alms<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175639:19"/>&amp;c. The not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this, hath made a miſunderſtanding of ſom of the Fathers in this matter.</p>
               <p>Truly ſometimes they pray expreſly, that they may enter Heaven before the laſt day, as St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> upon the death of <hi>Theodoſius: Dilexi, &amp; ideo proſequar eum uſque ad regionem vivorum, nec deſeram donec fletu, &amp; precibus inducam eum, quo ſua merita vocant, in montem Domini ſanctum, &amp;c.</hi> he will never leave praying, till by his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and teares he hath
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175639:19"/>brought him out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to Heaven. We need no more for both <hi>Churches:</hi> he a great <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Biſhop</hi> well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſenſe of both Churches, promiſeth this for the <hi>Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Emperor,</hi> in preſence of the Emperor; alſo a <hi>Grecian</hi> born, and of the <hi>Court</hi> where were preſent as well <hi>Greeke</hi> as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Prelats, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. If this had not been the publick ſenſe of all <hi>Churches</hi> in their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequies for the dead, there wanted not Zelots then, and after, who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:175639:20"/>would have reprehended this publique attempt, which you call <hi>Novelty,</hi> by them adjudged <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtome Homil.</hi> 41. <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>ad Cor.</hi> after a long diſcourſe ſaith thus: <hi>Si Jobi illius liberos pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris victima purgavit,</hi> (Job. 1.5.) <hi>quid dubites e nobis quoque ſi pro dormientibus offeramus, ſolatium quiddam ill is acceſſurum?</hi> This <hi>ſome comfort</hi> concludes a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent change upon our Prayers: this cannot ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>Heaven,</hi> where is no ſuch diminutive, as <hi>quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175639:20"/>ſolatium:</hi> this ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cannot be <hi>Doomſday;</hi> which agrees with Saint <hi>Auguſtines, Neque negan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, defunctorum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas pietate ſuorum viven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium relevari, cum pro il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſacrificium Mediatoris offertur, vel eleemoſynae in Eccleſia fiunt, &amp;c.</hi> 9.2. <hi>ad Dulcitium:</hi> and in his <hi>Enchyridion</hi> to <hi>Lawrence c.</hi> 110. as elſewhere he diſtinguiſhes three ſorts of the dead, whereof the midle are only capable of this help, and in his <hi>Care of the dead, c.</hi> 4. he tels us, that Chriſtians in their Prayers <hi>recommend the</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:175639:21"/>third <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Saints.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> take them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpany when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> riſe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you; but S. <hi>Aug.</hi> dre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd not of that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowſhip, but preſent eaſe, for ſurely S. <hi>Aug.</hi> his eaſing them is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent change. I could ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it faſtidious to the Reader, if I ſhould bring in particular the ſenſe of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Fathers, which, in reading them, I have noted. And though ſome <hi>Criticks</hi> do not give a due eſteem of S. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the great, and Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:175639:21"/>
                  <hi>Bede</hi> their Hiſtories, which <hi>Baronius</hi> elegantly defends; yet no man of reaſon can doubt, much leſſe deny, but that their loud approbation of the particular releaſes of ſouls, and the worlds not reſiſting their truth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly declare the ſenſe of the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world to have been, That <hi>by Prayers ſoules might be delivered out of Purgatory, before the laſt day.</hi> Nay, they did not only not reſiſt them, but both <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latines</hi> poſitively approved of them. For Pope <hi>Zachary</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:175639:22"/>had his bookes of <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues,</hi> without any reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in ſo high eſteem, that he himſelfe with his approbation, tranſlated, and recomended them to the <hi>Greeks.</hi> And S. <hi>John Damaſeen,</hi> and other <hi>Greeks,</hi> with much reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence received, and often cited them, as I have fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently noted: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder, that Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Bede,</hi> following our firſt Chriſtian Maſter, St. <hi>Gregory</hi> (though he himſelfe ſharp-ſighted) gives more examples of the like; as alſo S. <hi>John Damaſcen.</hi> Theſe two
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175639:22"/>(conſidering the eminency of their virtue and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and both great Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of antiquity, and both received as Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of truth in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Eaſt and Weſt Churches) may alone ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to witneſs the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Doctrine. <hi>Now</hi> (as S. Aug. c. 10. <hi>in his Care of the Dead,</hi> ſaith) <hi>if we ſhould ſay, that theſe things were falſe, we might be thought to uſe more boldneſſe than became us, both in regard of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of ſome faithfull Chriſtians who report it, as alſo in regard of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175639:23"/>teſtimony and ſenſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of thoſe, to whom ſuch viſions have hapned.</hi> May not this juſtly be applied here?</p>
               <p>Alſo conſider who St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> Pope <hi>Zachary,</hi> and St. <hi>Chriſo ſtom</hi> were, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> carry on their backs both the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Churches. And hence the Councel of <hi>Florence</hi> in the very Decree (as I have noted in another Book) ſpeaking for, and in the name of both Churches, ſayes: <hi>We define,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that thoſe ſouls, who, after they have contracted the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175639:23"/>of ſin, are purged either in their bodies, or, being uncloathed of their bodies, are preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into Heaven:</hi> and Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reſumption of their bodies.</hi> We can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no more as to the Doctrine of both Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; ſince, as you ſee, the Decree is conſonant to both.</p>
               <p>It's true that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Lyturgie</hi> in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia</hi> doth wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inculcate the horror of Doomſday, partly to move us living to a right apprehenſion of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175639:24"/>in it; partly that the dead may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive comfort before the laſt terrible day. Neither can the words have any other ſenſe: for certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſouls in <hi>Purgatory</hi> are not ambiguous of their judgement in that day, as all Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: and therefore the Church concluding, prays to God, to give all the Faithfull reſt from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, to prevent the rigour of that fearfull day.</p>
               <p>It's truly a miſtake to ſay, the <hi>Greek</hi> Church did not admit this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175639:24"/>before the <hi>Councel of Florence,</hi> ſince it is moſt evident, that their Doctrine was not at all changed, or diſliked even upon examination, as to this of <hi>eaſing,</hi> and <hi>deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſouls out of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or tranſlating them into <hi>Abraham's</hi> boſom by Prayers, &amp;c. but only in the beginning was exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined how far they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with Pope <hi>John</hi>'s errour againſt the facial ſight of God; and this was amended by common conſent. Nay, their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice was never queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or doubted of: which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175639:25"/>was, and is, the ſame with the <hi>Latines,</hi> as hath been ſhewed; and therefore <hi>Cyril</hi> repeating, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the manner of their Lyturgies, ſaith: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. That is, We believe that it will be a <hi>wonderfull help to the ſouls,</hi> for whom ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is offered of this holy and terrible ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Can any man refer this <hi>wonderfull help</hi> to a cold expectation of Doomſday? And hence we ſee in the third action of the General Councel of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> how the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175639:25"/>was admitted of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyrion</hi> againſt <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> for not having diſtributed faithfully, the abundant Alms by Legacy left to Monaſteries, for the ſouls of the deceaſed, which uniformly agrees with the Modern practiſe of both Churches; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doubtleſs the ſenſe of both Churches, as now they appear evidently to be the ſame; ſo in all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity they were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, as to hope of relief by prayers, eſpecially by Maſſes, as there is clear, and in many private <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Synods.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:175639:26"/>
               <p> Neither can it be other than a great <hi>Sophiſm</hi> to accuſe the <hi>Roman Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Offertory,</hi> as if in praying to deliver the ſouls of the Faithfull <hi>a poenis inferni;</hi> which is a general term ſignifying both, and ſo uſed, it ſhould import any thing elſe here, than from the <hi>pains of Purgatory</hi> to life: which cannot have any other ſenſe than of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> ſince there is no redemption in Hell; and the ſouls for which they pray, die no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:175639:26"/>
               <p> Again, the Church in the Collects prayes to give them <hi>refrigerii ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,</hi> &amp;c. a ſeat of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, which ſpeaks our <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Theſe and all other Texts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us of the Churches ſenſe of praying to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them before the great day: however by ſtrengh of wit the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt actions may be in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to weaker judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made dubious, as we ſee in <hi>Courts,</hi> the beſt cauſes by corrupted <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates,</hi> ſo clouded, that they ſeem unjuſt. But the knowledge of this is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175639:27"/>ſo univerſal, that here may be ſaid what St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, lib. de duabus anim. c.</hi> 12, ſaith of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>Nonne iſta cantant &amp; in montibus paſtores, &amp; theatris Poetae, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docti in circulis, &amp; docti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Bibliothecis, &amp; Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri in ſcholis, &amp; antiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in locis ſacris, &amp; in orbe terrarum genus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum.</hi> All ſorts of Chriſtians, each in their ſeveral poſtures, and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations witneſs this truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:175639:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Traditions alone cannot prove faith in all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis was S. <hi>Hieroms,</hi> and all the Fathers <hi>one</hi> (though not <hi>only</hi>) conſtant teſt of new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. And you profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly eſteeming the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the preſent age to conveigh certainly the ſenſe of the precedent, do, and muſt conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold it to be an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble teſt, to diſcern even matters of Faith: ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175639:28"/>that <hi>ad hominem</hi> this were ſtrong, if we had onely the preſent age. But ſurely <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Traditions</hi> are the ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate ſource of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an truths</hi> in the received opinion of Doctors. And the <hi>Councel of Trent</hi> in the firſt Seſſion ſeems to ſuppoſe it in order to the general. And truly all the former Councels did no leſs. Neither can I ſee that your <hi>Topick</hi> alone will ſalve all occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> refers the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> to his Epiſtles and Sermons joyntly: and S.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:175639:28"/>
                  <hi>Irenaeus l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4. ſhews the neceſſity of both: So S. <hi>Aug.</hi> and the reſt.</p>
               <p>But by endeavouring to infringe any pretence of a definition, as to this of helping ſouls in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory before Doomſday, you ſtruck upon a <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> which, if not rightly underſtood, is of an ill conſequent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:175639:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Charity conſiſts with Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory. The various operations of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Wherein conſiſts the chiefeſt penalty of Purgatory.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the purport of your diſcourſe ſeems to hint at this, that a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of retention of ſouls out of heaven till due <hi>penal expiation</hi> be accompliſht, will ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the dignity of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>Cicero lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> ſaith notably, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Philoſophy: <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:175639:29"/>dicere ornare velle, puerile eſt: plane autem, &amp; perſpicue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire poſſe, docti, &amp; intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentis eſt viri.</hi> Your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt connatural obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty renders you ſometimes to be miſconſtrued, to your prejudice. It is true, that charity, if perfect, is a ſufficient diſpoſition to glory; at leaſt as far as relates to excluſion of puniſhment for former tranſgreſſions: which ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily concludes, a ſoul dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that perfect condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to need any other temporary expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the midle ſort
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:175639:30"/>of Chriſtians, who onely have their concernment in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> according to Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and the Councel of <hi>Florence,</hi> though they die indeed in charity, yet is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to be ſo intenſe, as wholly to diſpoſe their ſouls for preſent bliſſe. And therefore in order to ſuch, the Church aſſerts further expiation, and penal detention, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for a longer or a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter terme, according to the ſecret rules of Gods wiſdom: wherein though our time is not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſpiritual ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:175639:30"/>or ſufferings, which have no parts to anſwer to the parts of our time, and therefore are not greater, or leſſe, for the extrinſecal, and diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate conſideration of a ſhorter, or longer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, preciſely as to time; yet their inward neceſſity of exiſting in that condition of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not only from their bodies, but from the ſight of God in the dregs of ſin, till God changeth them, is highly penable, as being alwaies preſent to their intuition, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: whereas in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:175639:31"/>where every thing is meaſured by motion, it would be far leſs, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſucceſſion of parts, than now being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to the nature of eviternity, which ſurely renders it incomparably greater, than if it were by one part after another. And though it is indiviſible as to its eſſence, and exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, being ſpiritual; and therefore cannot be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured otherwiſe than by a proportionable in-divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meaſure, as now I will ſuppoſe againſt ſome others; yet it hath
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:175639:31"/>co-exiſtence with the parts of our time, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> 4. <hi>Phyſ.</hi> ſaith: <hi>Idem nunc ſecundum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam differt ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſſe:</hi> that is, although an inſtant is the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſible in order to it ſelf, yet it differs as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to time. And hence a ſoul, which hath been in Purgatory twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, is truly ſaid to have been longer there than another, which was ſeperate from the body yeſterday; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently hath ſuffered the hard conſequences of it, even altogether ſo long.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:175639:32"/>
               <p> If we ſpeculate this a little further, we find, that as indeed the ſoul being in-diviſible, it hath an in-diviſible meaſure; yet as that inſtant, or meaſure called Aeviterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is alwaies and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſent; ſo there is alwaies preſent in it a priority, which we call of nature. As Agents which are free, in the ſame real inſtant, when they reſolve to do any thing, have a priority of nature, wherein it is not affirmable, that they do reſolve, but are as it were about to do it: and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:175639:32"/>this continues ſo long, as the real inſtant it ſelf doth. And therefore <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> will tell us, that the will, even when it doth decree any thing, it hath power not to do it, that is, as referring to that priority of nature. Whence followes even in your own principles, that the ſoul, which went to Purgatory many years agoe, is now as capable to have an act which it never had, as then, and therefore it may be as truly ſaid to have an act this day, which it never had; and conſequently
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:175639:33"/>may as truly be ſaid to be changed. But this whole matter is fitter for the Schooles to diſpute, then for Chatechizers to inſtruct in matter of Faith: of which more hereafter.</p>
               <p>You ſeem under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of putting a due eſtimate upon an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted or a Metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>charity</hi> (for ſuch yours almoſt ſeems to be) very much to undervalue her operations in ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal acts, or paſſions, as holy Church preſents to our belief in the dead. Nay, even all other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:175639:33"/>afflictions, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities in this life, voluntarily undertaken, you are thought to judge <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> (if not <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi>) and derogatory to chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>You know how far our neighbours have, by ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging this, reduced all Chriſtian duties of this kind, to ſuch a pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God in ſpirit, that there is no viſible footſtep of any old au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities amongſt them: and even all theſe old ſymptomes of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are with them by a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:175639:34"/>new ſort of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> evaporated.</p>
               <p>It ſeems certain, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the received doctrine of great Divines, (wherein you doe not wholly diſſent) that all ſouls, which depart from their bodies, in a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Heaven, at their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, do appretiate God above all, and do heartily deſire, that they had never placed any created object in his room; which is, never to have ſinned mortally. Which doctrine methinks is conſequent to St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> his opinion of infants
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:175639:34"/>in their firſt act of reaſon, applying themſelves to God. And this act, as I ſaid, is eſteemed natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indelible in the dead, according to their ſtate, with which is conſiſtent a deſire of fulfilling Gods Laws, in order to expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of former ſins: nay, that is inconſiſtent with it ſelf, without a deſire of complyance with Gods ordinances, in this and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very other kind. Whence follows, that their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings after death, are vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, as relating to their former acts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Gods orders,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:175639:35"/>and the virtual or habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual durance of it; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever by ſome, ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable a truth is denied.</p>
               <p>The whole univerſe therefore having been <hi>deformed</hi> in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by our <hi>deordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> it muſt be <hi>reform'd</hi> by our <hi>pennances.</hi> For, according to Divines, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligitur poena, ut ordine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur culpa:</hi> and it is ſo, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven following nature. So that the order of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, by Gods original poſition of cauſes, exacts this method of us. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no neceſſity, which ſome are affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:175639:35"/>at ſo much, to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute their penal detenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>revenge</hi> in God; (though it is but <hi>quaeſtio de nomine,</hi> as diverſly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) ſince it is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to our peccaminous acts, to be liable to it; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially holding, as truth ſeems to convince, that the reliques of the ſinnes themſelves, or thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſins, of which the ſouls were guilty in death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main till the change of the ſouls after <hi>Purgation.</hi> Which doctrine is very conformable to <hi>Scotus;</hi> who holds, that <hi>venial ſins after proportionable
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:175639:36"/>puniſhment in hell it ſelf, ceaſe to be;</hi> that is, after the remorſe and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, proportionable to ſuch ſin, ceaſe; which, as I have noted elſewhere, is <hi>Origen</hi>'s and <hi>Gregorie Niſſenes</hi> clear doctrine: for they both ſeem to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that only <hi>Purgatory.</hi> I ſaid <hi>puniſhments,</hi> for which we now call pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as to the minds remorſe for ſin, in time of nature we would call effects of ſin, as I ſhewed, <hi>de Mundo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its true, we have not injured God in our ſins, who is above, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:175639:36"/>the ſpheres of our moſt malitious activity; but our ſelves are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally endamaged in mortal ſins, by loſing all title to Heaven, or at leaſt, by diminiſhing it, as in <hi>venial.</hi> Which loſſe cauſed by violation of his Lawes, muſt be repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by charity, directing to ſubmit to, and to keep Gods Commandments, according to that Text of our Saviour: <hi>If you love me, keep my Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements:</hi> whereof one is, to ſubmit to his orders in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> wherein this voluntary due cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:175639:37"/>at laſt will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure remiſſion of thoſe ſins, which remain, at the leaſt in their dregs.</p>
               <p>Charity indeed hath God himſelf, under the nobleſt motives, for its immediate object; but it is exerciſed, not onely in a naked wiſhing, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling well to God, which is to love him; but it breaks out into a hearty complyance with all his orders. Hence St. <hi>Peter, John</hi> the laſt Chapter, v. 15. being demanded, whether <hi>he loved God?</hi> to his triplicated affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was as often ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:175639:37"/>
                  <hi>Feed my ſheep, &amp;c.</hi> So that this love hath a great extent, though it alwaies terminates in God, as it begins in him. St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. tells us ſummarily, but <hi>pathetically,</hi> the further operation of charity: <hi>Charitas patiens est, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigna est, &amp;c.</hi> whence will follow, that charity can be exerciſed, in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing any of Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in reſpect of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or the dead, as in thoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. who were <hi>baptized,</hi> that is, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the dead, as
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:175639:38"/>the Text clearly ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>It is not then any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity to charity, that good Chriſtians dying inveſted with it, ſhould be exerciſed afterwards in expiation of former deordinations, by their paſſive complyance with Gods orders; which, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in charity, they could not but deſire. This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine order being fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and expiation being effected, the ſoul is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, through Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, capable of her hoped ſuperveſtition of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:175639:38"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>How a ſoul, according to others, can change. Of the horror of Doomes-day. Whether it is to be prayed for.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I will now ſuppoſe that borrowed principle out of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Schooles, that <hi>the ſoul is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any change, once ſeparated from the body,</hi> as having not the fancy, whence the changes were occaſioned. Which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine although I have taught in my <hi>System,</hi> and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:175639:39"/>ſo do St. <hi>Thomas</hi> in his School, <hi>Henricus de Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davo,</hi> and others, as to natural cauſes; yet it will not reach ſo far, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as to build a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, ſo remote from the common ſenſe of Chriſtians, as this of all ſoules, which do not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately go to Heaven, or to Hel, their preſtola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt day in Purgatory, and that then upon the reunion of their bodies, our bleſſed Lord ſhall repreſent to our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral eies his moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed humanity: of which he made us not capable
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:175639:39"/>during our long expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſoules ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: upon ſight whereof they ſhall fall into rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of divine love, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The whole complex taken altogether, is the product of a great wit, poſſeſſed of much lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and, if kept within the Schooles (as we uſe frequently impoſſible ſuppoſitions) might exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe wits with profit, and applauſe, as I believe was intended: but where it toucheth upon a noble particle of our <hi>Religion,</hi> as here, the putting it into a vernacular Idiome is
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:175639:40"/>
                  <hi>dangerous,</hi> and againſt the <hi>Councel of Trent,</hi> in in this particular, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Apud rudem verò plebem difficiliores, ac ſubtiliores quaeſtiones, quaeque ad ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificationem non faciunt, &amp; ex quibus plerunque nulla fit pietatis acceſſio, a popularibus concionibus ſecludantur: incerta item, vel quae ſpecie falſi labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, evulgari, ac tractari, non permittant, &amp;c.</hi> This comes home. We are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to move theſe queſtions in Engliſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prayer for the Dead,</hi> as for ſuch as are helped by it, being in an indigent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:175639:40"/>condition, is one of the moſt univerſal, moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and moſt ſolemn practiſes of <hi>holy Church,</hi> as all Monuments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare: which by this your ſpeculation is rendred, ſpeaking really, of no uſe; as being reſolved by you onely into a Prayer for <hi>Doomſday:</hi> which will be terrible, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it cometh; as holy Church intimates in the <hi>Sequentia: Cùm vix ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus ſit ſecurus;</hi> and <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus tremor eſt futurus.</hi> I am ſure S. <hi>Hierom</hi> had a formidable apprehenſion of it, when he ſaith, <hi>He
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:175639:41"/>heard perpetually the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſound of the trumpet:</hi> and you hear how holy Church deſcribes it, even in order to the juſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of whom, S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 10. of the Hebrews cals it, <hi>Terribilis quaedam expectatio judicii,</hi> a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible expectation of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and hence S. <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius in Pſal.</hi> 113. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo deſiderabile poteſt eſſe judicium, in quo nobis eſt indefeſſus ille ignis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eundus? &amp;c.</hi> How can that day be an object of our Prayers? &amp;c. The very Saints themſelves muſt paſſe through that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:175639:41"/>laſt fire, but as ſilver and gold: which can ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſevere teſt: &amp; this being done, they muſt be Judges of us ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The Apoſtle ſaith both. Out of which if we weigh the inexplicable ſeverity of that day, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderare quis audebit?</hi> who, with S. <hi>Hilary,</hi> dare pray for it? and yet your main poſition is, that this is only prayed for, and that, till that great day, the Saints, though in an indigent condition, are not capable to receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>refrigerium,</hi> or eaſe, as the Fathers ſpeak, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:175639:42"/>expreſly prayed for in all the Churches Liturgies. Which is indeed a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe <hi>tenet</hi> to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and it toucheth too near upon the <hi>Church,</hi> and her doctrine, though moſt Sectaries will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud it.</p>
               <p>Shall I tell you how near it preſſeth upon this Article? Truly (beſides what I ſaid in the former Chapters) I know not poſſibly, how to render <hi>the prayers of holy Church for the dead,</hi> of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable uſe at all, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to, and for them, either in particular, or in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:175639:42"/>general, as they are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinct</hi> from the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful living. I ſpoke before, that this <hi>tenet</hi> renders prayers for particular dead perſons uſeleſs, as not at all correſponding with the deſign of their friends, which evidently was, and is intended by all, in order to obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of eaſe and relief of ſuch ſouls, for which they pray. But now by further weighing the neceſſary conſequences of this <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> it ſeems evidently to conclude, all prayers for the dead, in effect uſeleſs, even as offered in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:175639:43"/>or for all in general, as well as for particular perſons.</p>
               <p>The reaſon is; firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if we pray only for the general Reſurrection, (as you ſay) this concerns them not any more, nay, leſs, as being dead, than if they were living: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are already ſure of a happy reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; &amp; in ſome degree, though yet in a ſtate of puniſhment, as it were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready poſſeſt of it, or at leaſt, upon entring into it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, in order to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:175639:43"/>Heaven, is ſo urgent in reſpect of the faithfull living, and being yet wholly in the clouds, in reſpect of our knowledg, or any certainty of it, that our Prayers in true charity, ought to be far more fervent &amp; conſtant, for all the faithful living, as being in more neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than for the dead, or at leaſt, for them both together, if this be all we are to pray for, by the Churches definition.</p>
               <p>Whence methinks it concludes, that the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of praying for the dead, either for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:175639:44"/>or generals, is upon very ſlight grounds preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and obſerved by holy Church in your princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſurely they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that the ſame pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers which are offred for the dead, ought to be offred, either for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dead together, or elſe principally for the living. Whence follows, that there is no need at all of this article, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the dead, as I ſaid, condiſtinct from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; if there be no hope of preſent reliefe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe, till the general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. I do but give
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:175639:44"/>you a hint, that you may further reflect upon it. This done, I proceed to the ground it ſelf of your aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Indeed the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the World, and of the Schools, S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Alexander Hales, S. Bonaventure, Scotus</hi> in his book <hi>de anima,</hi> and many other eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not eſteeming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to deſert <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> teach us, the ſouls have a natural capacity of ſom change without the body.</p>
               <p>One ground is, they conceive the impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of change to be deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:175639:45"/>originally from the negation of matter (which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> aſſerts <hi>principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um corruptionis</hi>) which is ſuppoſed to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all ſpirituall things: but if materiality be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the limited ſimplicity of our ſouls, as they endeavour to prove in <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> principles; ſince they have <hi>individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> and ſome <hi>compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in their ſeparated ſtate from the bodies, as they conceive to be clear in <hi>Metaphiſical</hi> ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: which if true, their conſequence is eaſie for what relates to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:175639:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Do you examine this: it wants not great weight, even the force of <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi> in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>Again, S. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> holds <hi>Aeviternity</hi> to have a ſort of diviſibility; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I ſhall explicate in due place: his reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe otherwiſe it will argue ſouls, and Angels to have actually infinite durance, being their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance continues <hi>in infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> as all ſuppoſe which he eſteems a great abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to aſſert of any finite thing; as arguing infinite
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:175639:46"/>vertue to require infinite durance <hi>together:</hi> which will conclude them to be infinite in eſſence; which is againſt all our ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
               <p>In the ſame manner will as eaſily be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that a ſeparate ſoul hath actually an infinite knowledge of things; ſince the inſtant of aevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, which is immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and <hi>altogether,</hi> continues <hi>in infinitum,</hi> and conſequently hath infinite objects preſent: of all which the ſoul act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually, and by its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural power, produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:175639:46"/>knowledge <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> which argues infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite vigor.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Bonavent.</hi> and the reſt, eſteem both theſe repugnant to a creature; though you ſhould ſay, that each is derived from God: for ſtill it ſtands that the ſoul from its own nature, though derived from God, is <hi>infiniti vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goris:</hi> which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> juſtly appropriates to God. Examine this, and weigh well, whether it doth not imply contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</p>
               <p>I aſſure you that theſe preſt home, will ſooner
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:175639:47"/>be heightned to a <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi> than moſt of thoſe, which are urged for the contrary, with loud intonations of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations.</hi> But if in <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> which are rendred pervious to our ſences, we cannot reach to <hi>demonſtrations,</hi> but upon ſwallowing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuppoſitions without proof, what can we vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloriouſly boaſt of, in theſe remote objects?</p>
               <p>Its true, that a ſoul ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, cannot produce new habits in it ſelf by acts, as now we do, by reaſon it hath all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:175639:47"/>diſpoſition already, as being determined by nature to it; yet it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with its <hi>aeviterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that the ſoul have ſome new acts, at leaſt in order to ſupernatural objects. Thus far S. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Scotus,</hi> and all agree; as Angels in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are recorded to have had in divers occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Thomas, Henricus,</hi> and others, to make this good, invent a ſort of time; which they call, <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus diſcretum,</hi> (though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> never heard of it) to meaſure them by,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:175639:48"/>that is, where there is not a continuation by parts, as in our time, but each inſtant followes without ties. But I think there is no need to explicate one obſcurity by a greater: for indeed it is hard to conceive what one indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible added to another, will have for the <hi>quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> but <hi>punctum;</hi> which will leave us where we were. And therefore ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this rode, I think it clear, that the ſouls have acts; and that, according to their natures, they are meaſured by <hi>aeviternity,</hi> in its proper ſenſe; as
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:175639:48"/>
                  <hi>Scotus,</hi> and the reſt, teach: though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> out of a falſe principle of the ſouls abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon the <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> denies a ſeparated ſoul to have any act at all: but <hi>Avicen</hi> ſaith bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, following <hi>Platoes,</hi> and, as he contends, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles</hi> doctrin, as I have done in the <hi>System,</hi> that <hi>the ſoul hath the ſpecies of all things within it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others conceive, that without them, it hath actual knowledge of all: and therefore, as to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral objects, the ſoul in ſtate of ſeparation hath
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:175639:49"/>knowledge of all; and conſequently (as they think) is eaſily proved not to be ſubject to change in them: and which is very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Mr. <hi>White</hi> goes no further, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>lect.</hi> 4. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans itaque eſt, nullam mutationem ex naturae vi, in anima ſeparata poſſe exiſtere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:175639:49"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Whether a ſoul can be changed by God, and how, in Purgatory? The true ſtate of the controverſie explicated.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt when we ſpeak of the ſoul in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> we ſpeak of a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral condition: in which caſe, notwithſtanding its ſpirituallity, it is movea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by objects of a ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior order, (neither do I remember, that Maſter <hi>White</hi> queſtioneth this) of which it hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:175639:50"/>any <hi>ſpecies.</hi> Neither doth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of any thing to a being after it had none, hinder it from being ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, or aeviternal: elſe Angels, and our ſouls created in time, though not ſucceſſively, or in the parts of time would miſs of both.</p>
               <p>For example: what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance is there in the ſoul to be moved, if God ſhall pleaſe to preſent his bleſſed humanity to it in the ſtate of ſeparation, as well as when it is again joyned to the body? tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I doubt not, but it
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:175639:50"/>would produce a far more noble, and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe act, of the love of God in its ſeparation; being far more powerful then, when it is united to the body, when it works onely by help, and order, of the fancy: as it muſt doe according to courſe of nature, at the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition of that bleſſed object; being the ſoul is ſuppoſed not to be yet beatified.</p>
               <p>I ſee not that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality renders the ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and it is certain, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> thought it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:175639:51"/>not ſo: whence he cryes: <hi>Sive in corpore, ſive ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra corpus, neſcio.</hi> He would have known, if his ſoul <hi>extra corpus,</hi> that is, in her ſpirituallity, had repugned to the viſion.</p>
               <p>If it be replyed, that this is ſupernatural.</p>
               <p>Is it not ſo, that the ſoul at laſt is reunited to the bodie; when you conceive it ſhall love God more intenſely? Nay is it not ſo, that all ill affections, which it carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of this world, ſhall remain till the reunion, and then be aboliſhed? What natural <hi>reaſon</hi> will
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:175639:51"/>
                  <hi>reach</hi> this? Nay, what principles of <hi>Religion</hi> will <hi>teach</hi> us, that the ſouls of good Chriſtians (for ſo they muſt be) ſhall be detained in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> ſo many ages com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in aeviternity, as till Doomſday to no effect in order to the ſoules; ſince the very dregs of ſin, with which they parted from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and their ill affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are not at all correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or purged, by occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that ſtate, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main till after the reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all their degrees of intention? ſo that their
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:175639:52"/>remainder there, ſeems uſeleſſe, &amp; indeed pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vindicative: againſt which you much inſiſt.</p>
               <p>Again, the whole ſtate of the ſoul here treated, is ſupernatural, that is, under another <hi>ſeries</hi> of cauſes, then being with the body. That the ſoul continues in the ſtate of ſin, or dregs of it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is at the time of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual remorſe, or ſting of conſcience, according to that of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> c. 18. to the rich man: <hi>Recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quia recepiſti bona in vita tua:</hi> Remember
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:175639:52"/>what good things thou receivedſt in thy life. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in a moſt afflictive, and almoſt a vexatious deſire of <hi>Heaven:</hi> from which, as they know, ſins, or the dregs, retard them. All this is natural to it: but that this ſtate is tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, and relating, or tending, to a change of eternal felicity; and that it is <hi>poenal,</hi> that is, <hi>infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> as ſuch, is above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. (I meddle not here with, what other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, do, or may, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company this ſtate.) No wonder then, if in this ſupernatural condition,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:175639:53"/>it hath, when God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, theſe ſupernatural viſits, by wayes, which we know not; in which, the ſoul is ſubject to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: this I conceive ſufficient for the matter here treated, which is, the ſouls change in order to Heaven.</p>
               <p>To deny this to the ſouls, is not to call in queſtion their naturall power, in which we are already agreed, as to the negative; but Gods po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, in order to them, which in our conference you granted.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:175639:53"/>
               <p> Whereas it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that ſtill here is no diverſity of parts, as an <hi>Agent</hi> and a <hi>Patient,</hi> in an indiviſible ſoule: which is required in all actions, even to avoid contradiction.</p>
               <p>To this is replied, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>de An. verſus fin.</hi> as <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Bacon</hi> and <hi>Gulielmus Pariſienſis,</hi> and others, interpret him, that God is therefore, as <hi>intellectus agens,</hi> who illuminates our underſtanding by a ſpiritual light, as the Sun doth our ſight, in order to bodies; and ſo actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:175639:54"/>it, in order to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things, whereof it is capable: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, that <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus agens</hi> is ſeparated <hi>a poſſibili,</hi> ſubſtantially; and that it knowes all things; and that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in act, &amp;c. which are proper to God, as they think: and indeed to make the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be <hi>agens</hi> and <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilis,</hi> it is a riddle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is to make it <hi>Agent</hi> and <hi>Patient</hi> to it ſelf, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indiviſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:175639:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>The ſtate of the Queſtion further explicated. The difference between an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of time and aevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity declared. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Queſtion fully given, as to change of ſouls.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF you ask me, how a Soul, by the power of God can be chang'd, from a not knowing to a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the ſame inſtant, without contradiction?</p>
               <p>I anſwer firſt, that our ſouls are indeed indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their eſſences; as
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:175639:55"/>not having quantity; &amp; in the production of their acts, or operations, in ſtate of ſeparation; as being not done by moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: they are alſo indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible in their durances; or the meaſures of their durances are indiviſible; that is, not by parts: with which is conſiſtent, that their meaſures are not inſtantaneous, as ours are; but are capable, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, upon Gods conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated, and, as it were, connatural influence, as the beames in reſpect of the Sun, to include the whole preſentiality of ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:175639:55"/>by reaſon that the length, or ſhortneſſe of duration doth not at all change the meaſure in it ſelf; provided that it be altogether.</p>
               <p>It is therefore a great diſproportion, rather a colluſion, to argue from the conſideration of an inſtant of our time to ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viternity: they both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in this, that they are indiviſible; that is, they are not capable of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of parts: but the reaſon of this in each is wholly different.</p>
               <p>The inſtant of time is therfore ſo, becauſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſically
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:175639:56"/>ſpeaking, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egation, or termination of ſome thing, and hath therefore no duration at all <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vum,</hi> or aeviternity, is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſucceſſion, as being, as the former is, indiviſible, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but yet hath infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite durance, according to the way expreſſed, vertually including infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite inſtances, according to which it is conceivable to have mutation without contradiction; becauſe its durance or exiſtence now, though altogether, or not by parts, is not by
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:175639:56"/>vertue of the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, or influx, it hath from God, as appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before; but it hath, in a manner, a new depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy of him, elſe both it, and its meaſure would ceaſe to be: this is both <hi>Scotus</hi> and S. <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> ſolid way of expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this abſtruſe difficulty. And truly I believe St. <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Henricus</hi> their <hi>tempus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum,</hi> well weighed, will fall into it. And ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily <hi>Aeviternity</hi> ſeems in this to differ from <hi>aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> that it doth not neceſſarily involve an
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:175639:57"/>impoſſibility of ceaſing to be, or of requiring a continuated, or, as it were, a new dependance of the divine influence, without which it would ceaſe: Whereas, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is eſſentially <hi>aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> is repugnant to any imaginable change; and therefore it can onely be aſſerted of God.</p>
               <p>I could anſwer ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that in the operations of Angels, or ſouls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as to the ſimple notion of their aeviterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, there may be ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or mutation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction (which
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:175639:57"/>
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> grants without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction.) My reaſon is, becauſe the aſſertion, or negation of any operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is in reſpect of divers inſtances, or aeviternal meaſures.</p>
               <p>For example, the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a ſoul is its own meaſure, as not being diſtinct from it: the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations have, or are, each theirs, as being indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as well as the ſoul. Hence, although the ſoul, as to <hi>eſſence</hi> and <hi>exiſtence,</hi> is immutable, as natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly its meaſure is; and ſo each operation is, whilſt it is, or its <hi>aevum</hi> is: yet
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:175639:58"/>the ſoul, as to operation, or under operation, may, without contradiction, admit ſome change, as lying under other <hi>aeviter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> or meaſures, which accompany the <hi>Acts,</hi> as I have ſaid. Whence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that the ſoul is not rightly ſaid to be <hi>not knowing,</hi> and <hi>knowing,</hi> in the ſame, or in order to the ſame <hi>inſtant,</hi> or <hi>aevum;</hi> but it is <hi>not knowing,</hi> as meaſured by the ſoul's own <hi>aevum,</hi> and it is <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> conſidered as to the meaſures of the <hi>Acts,</hi> which as I declared, muſt be diſtinct from that of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:175639:58"/>the Soul: and hence it may have new <hi>Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, I anſwer, that rightly putting with <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that <hi>Aevum,</hi> or how you will call the meaſure of Angelical, or <hi>Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick</hi> Natures, is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the things meaſured. You know in bodies the meaſures are extrinſecall as being from the motions of the bodies of the Heavens, but here is no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal <hi>Gnomon</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſpiritual ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. We need not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeek, whether they may have ſucceſſion of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:175639:59"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> in one inſtant, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void contradiction, which ſo much affrights us: but we onely are to look upon the nature of the <hi>Acts</hi> themſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is no implica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in them to co-exiſt with one another, or to ſucceed each other? Which ſure there is none imaginable. Neither do you alledge any here. It is not hard then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that a Soul hath many <hi>Acts;</hi> ſince alſo, as I ſaid above, an <hi>aevum</hi> can co-exiſt to an infinity of <hi>inſtances;</hi> namely, as long as an Angel continues.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:175639:59"/>
               <p> I hope, out of all this I may ſafely conclude, that a ſeparated ſoul may have <hi>mutation</hi> in its <hi>Acts,</hi> eſpecially as S. <hi>Thomas</hi> ſpeaks 2.2.9.58. a. 11. <hi>Quantum ad ea, quae eis divinitus revelantur, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil prohibet, intellectus Angelorum eſſe in poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My ſolution therefore is, that the Angels, or Souls, without contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, are capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, or whatſoever motions from God, that is, in any ſupernatural way; in order whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nothing hinders them
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:175639:60"/>to be changeable, and this, as I ſaid, is ſufficient for our principal aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſouls capacity of <hi>change,</hi> in <hi>Purgatory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, that the <hi>ſoul is a pure act,</hi> as admitting no compoſition; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>acts</hi> are not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the eſſence, and therefore not muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>It is as eaſie replyed, that it is repugnant to the nature of a creature to be that, which Divines call <hi>a pure act,</hi> firſt as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>potentiality</hi> to a not being, and having a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:175639:60"/>dependance upon <hi>compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition;</hi> or having ſome actual <hi>compoſition,</hi> or <hi>componibility.</hi> Alſo to have been produced out of nothing, carries with it a defect of that <hi>ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,</hi> which is a <hi>pure act,</hi> as having neceſſarily a <hi>quo,</hi> and <hi>quod.</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this very thing, an Angel (which is the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt of creatures) differs from God, that it is not its <hi>own act,</hi> and therefore in a <hi>potentiality</hi> to <hi>acts:</hi> which can not be ſaid of any but God. This is as to the <hi>general.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:175639:61"/>of a ſoul, render it far inferior, as being compounded Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſically, which is real. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, as cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it is ordinable to a <hi>Phyſical compoſition,</hi> as to be a part of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> or whole man: which excludes the being a pure <hi>act:</hi> for <hi>matter,</hi> and <hi>forme,</hi> are therefore not ſimple enough, as to this (though otherwiſe <hi>ſimpliciter ſimplices,</hi> as <hi>Scotus</hi> ſpeaks) becauſe they are <hi>componible</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt themſelves.</p>
               <p>Being advanced thus far, you will give me
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:175639:61"/>leave to tell you, that I do not conceive it to be out of ignorance of the nature of a ſoul (though it is thought ſo) that all Divines grant this ſort of <hi>mutability;</hi> which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Councels, Fathers,</hi> all <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reaſon,</hi> but it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a <hi>non</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertence of the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of holy Churches doctrine, confirmed by univerſal practice of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of ſouls out of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> before the great day, that now the contrary is ſo much preſſed by ſome,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:175639:62"/>as not conſidering their ſubjection to Gods pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful mercy.</p>
               <p>A modeſt man would rather ſay with St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> treating almoſt of this matter, for it is in his treatiſe of the <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Divels,</hi> cap. 6. <hi>Rem dixi occultiſſimam audaciore aſſeveratione, quam debui:</hi> I have been more bold than wiſe to ſpeak confidently in theſe remote ſubjects. Let us therefore return to the ſouls proceeding in <hi>Purgatory.</hi> For as to the other objections (which ordinarily are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged)
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:175639:62"/>they have more <hi>Water,</hi> than <hi>Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In order indeed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of <hi>Charity,</hi> the ſoul hath in <hi>Purgatory</hi> ſome <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already <hi>inveſted</hi> with it; but by reaſon firſt, that it is <hi>extra viam;</hi> by reaſon alſo of the <hi>dregs,</hi> which cauſe, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany its preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is not expeditely diſpoſed, but at length, according to Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by preſenting force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſome ſupernatural object, or motive, or ſome other way, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles are removed, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:175639:63"/>the ſoul eaſily intended to ſuch a <hi>charity,</hi> rather <hi>charity</hi> to ſuch a degree is intended in the ſoul; which joynes it to glory; each by waies unknown, as being unneceſſary to the Churches preſent condition, to know Gods waies in the ſouls relief; importing nothing to the advance of <hi>Piety;</hi> which as you will confeſs, is the <hi>border of revealed truths.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:175639:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Scriptures, and Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, muſt be obeyed. How one can ſatisſie for another. Whether, and how, other vertues, beſides Charity, avail towards Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat learned perſons uſe their abilities to declare the true ſenſe of <hi>Church-cuſtomes,</hi> where there may be miſtakes, is the office of <hi>Chriſtian Divines,</hi> and highly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy their endeavours: and the <hi>Councel of Trent</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:175639:64"/>enjoynes Prelates to do it in this particular, as St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> St. <hi>Bonav. Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and the reſt, do. But to call general, old cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes themſelves into queſtion, or to bend them to our ſpeculations, is, in St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> eſteem (<hi>ep.</hi> 118.) the greateſt madneſs in the world. His words are, <hi>inſolentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimae inſaniae eſt.</hi> His rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe, <hi>Quae uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa tenet eccleſia, ab A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolis praecepta, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne creduntur, quanquam ſcripta non reperiantur;</hi> as he rightly teaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Donatiſts, l.</hi>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:175639:64"/>5. <hi>c.</hi> 23. It is enough, if holy Church avoucheth any thing: yet you preſs this ſo far, as you ſeem to cenſure the publike ſence of all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> of <hi>novelty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> when they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon any Texts of Holy Scripture, which they found too hard for them (which was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent) they imputed it to <hi>their</hi> want of <hi>reaſon;</hi> and not to the <hi>Scriptures</hi> want of <hi>Truth.</hi> Hence St. <hi>Hierome</hi> Q. 8. <hi>ad Algaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> ſpeaking of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:175639:65"/>ſaith: <hi>Totus hic Apoſtoli locus, &amp; in ſuperioribus, &amp; in conſequentibus; imo omnis Epiſtola ejus ad Romanos, nimiis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritatibus involuta eſt.</hi> The whole Epiſtle was above his reach, yet he durſt not, in the leaſt, queſtion the <hi>truth,</hi> but confeſt his own <hi>weakneſs,</hi> and beſides many other places, in his thirtieth <hi>ep.</hi> which is, to <hi>Oceanus</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Fabiola,</hi> her pious deſire to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſome paſſages of holy Scripture in the book of <hi>Numbers,</hi> he tells her queſtions to him: To
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:175639:65"/>which, he thus recounts his anſwer. <hi>In quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam haeſitavi, in aliis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſo pede cucurri, in pleriſque ignorantiant confeſſus ſum.</hi> He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth he was not able to ſalve the propoſals, even of a woman, by reaſon of the intricaſies in the holy Text, yet he ſubmits to all. And no leſs in holy <hi>Churches Traditions,</hi> or <hi>univerſal cuſtomes,</hi> as you have heard St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> whereof this is one.</p>
               <p>Moſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having not at their deaths (as is ſuppoſed)
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:175639:66"/>ſo <hi>intenſe</hi> a <hi>charity,</hi> as could perfectly ordinate their faults (as <hi>Martyrs</hi> and great <hi>Saints</hi> are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly believed to have) hence after this life (that every <hi>coinquination,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, may be expurged) they are exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in a due <hi>ſatiſpaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in conformity to Gods orders, before entrance into Heaven. Which though <hi>formally</hi> can onely be performed by themſelves, yet <hi>aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valently</hi> by <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> tendred by the <hi>Church Militant,</hi> and her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, it may be eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:175639:66"/>
                  <hi>Theirs,</hi> as all Courts of Juſtice, eſpecially where there is a commix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Mercy,</hi> as in this caſe, will admit. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I know no <hi>Law,</hi> or expreſs <hi>inſtitution</hi> of God for this, whereby it may be expected in rigor of juſtice, or <hi>ex condigno,</hi> as we ſpeak, <hi>That one mans Act, ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted for another, but onely by way of Petition, and impetration;</hi> which the children of holy <hi>Church</hi> uſe, eſpecially for the <hi>faithful departed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When therefore all Chriſtians, even from the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:175639:67"/>time, when charity it ſelf in our bleſſed Lord dwelt amongſt us, did, and do, acknowledge <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> to be a <hi>poenitential,</hi> and <hi>humble Religion,</hi> as the Roman Perſecutors exprobrated to our Primitive Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; they did not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we, prefer exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Penances, and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liations before <hi>Charity, the Queen of Vertues:</hi> which only amongſt The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological Vertues ſtands the ſhock of Eternity, and which qualifies, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hances our Acts, in order to it; inſomuch that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:175639:67"/>
                  <hi>Prayers, Faſtings,</hi> or <hi>Alms-deeds,</hi> do avail, in order to Heaven, and for <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of ſins, as the <hi>Councel of Trent, Seſ.</hi> 14. declares; yet it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, that they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, or ordered by <hi>Charity;</hi> though the wiſe <hi>Councel</hi> doth not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine this. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we all deſire, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Laws of God, that <hi>Charity,</hi> which is <hi>free,</hi> according to the Apoſtle, may not be <hi>ſtraightned</hi> in its operations; but, as circumſtances invite, let it be imployed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one, by curing ſouls; in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:175639:68"/>by curing bodies; in a third, by corporal Pennances; in a fourth, by ſuffering <hi>for</hi> the dead, or <hi>in</hi> the dead, by ſuffering for themſelves, in each, according as the Spirit of God directs. As in the <hi>Collations of the Fathers, Col.</hi> 14. <hi>C.</hi> 4. <hi>Neſtorius</hi> the <hi>Abbot,</hi> ſpeaking of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſaith: Some choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the care of the ſick; ſome begging for people in miſery, or teaching the ignorant; or giving alms to the poor, &amp;c. were every one glorious in their ſeverall pieties:
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:175639:68"/>ſo that they were pieties, that is operations of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How corporal afflictions can ſatisfie for ſinnes? Whether a probable O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion may be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF we admit not this, we ſhall with <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his Verſion, content our ſelves with his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is, if wee will, for the future com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no more Theft, Adultery, or the like, there is no need of wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:175639:69"/>ſackcloth and aſhes, faſting, or any peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial works, though flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Charity, to take away the dregs of ſin, and ſo appeaſe God offended for them; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Scriptures, and ſenſe of all Chriſtians: which is indeed <hi>Calvin's Libertiniſm,</hi> never known before in the world, nor, as I preſume, by you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: expreſly alſo againſt the <hi>Councel. of Trent, Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14. which I entreat you to peruſe; for it condemns with <hi>Anathema</hi> to ſay, that <hi>Faſtings, Prayers,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:175639:69"/>and Alms, or other pious works through Chriſt, do not ſatisfie for temporal puniſhment due for our ſins;</hi> that is, after the guilt of them is taken away by the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>I do not ſay this, as if corporal auſterities, or indeed any thing elſe of ours were in their own natures proportionable ſatisfactions in order to God, for our violations of his Laws; but as all ſins, even thoſe which are purely mental, or that have not proceeded fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the will, are truly, even in <hi>Ariſtotle's</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:175639:70"/>grounds, operations of the whole man; for, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones ſunt ſuppoſitorum.</hi> Thus far Reaſon will carry us, that even the Body ſhould be <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> in aboliſhing thoſe guilts whereof it was <hi>partaker,</hi> and ſometimes a ſhrewd <hi>Suggeſtor.</hi> Whereupon we know, the moſt ſpeculative Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, as <hi>Scotus</hi> his School, and <hi>Cajetan,</hi> with many others teach, that even <hi>the ſenſitive,</hi> that is, <hi>the corporeal part of a man, hath a capacity of venial ſin in it ſelfe; and as of ſin, ſo of goodneſſe.</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:175639:70"/>Whence they rationally teach, that a man, who doth not onely intend, but effectually giveth Alms, or the like, doth add a degree of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may hope for a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reward, than if he had contained himſelfe within the bounds of his Will.</p>
               <p>Whence will further follow, that <hi>corporal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions,</hi> even in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, may properly ſerve as <hi>emanations</hi> from a ſoule afflicted for ſin, or as <hi>exerciſes,</hi> of which the body is only capable,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:175639:71"/>flowing from the love of God, as ſurely they are, in a true <hi>contrite ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this kinde in holy Writ, they are by true Penitents ſometimes voluntarily undertaken, other times by Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders inflicted, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in order to remiſſion of ſins; and this not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes miraculous, as the Texts of holy Scriptures ſhew. If it were mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous (as ſometimes it is, and you have well pondered,) it is ſo far from enervating, that it demonſtratively confirms
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:175639:71"/>Gods acceptance of the Churches Doctrine and practice, as to <hi>corporal afflictions,</hi> to the end aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned: as is alſo clearly ſhewed in the place quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the <hi>Councel of Trent:</hi> as alſo <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>And hence holy <hi>Church</hi> by Gods orders injoyns <hi>Sacramental pennances</hi> (theſe I know you do not reject) which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letory of the dregs of ſin, that is, they may exerciſe the ſoule in <hi>intending</hi> Charity infuſed by God upon ſorrow, and the efficacy of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:175639:72"/>By which means is often wrought an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute extinction of ſin, that is, even of thoſe <hi>veleities,</hi> which frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trouble us after the height of our former mortal malice, by help of the Sacraments (deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from our bleſſed Saviours Paſſion) was extinguiſhed and pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>As concerning ſome ſeeming excreſcencies, which you, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers carped at, and the like Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> alſo jeſted at, I believe no judicious Catholique wil
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:175639:72"/>pretend, that they have ſtrict acquaintance with Church Orders, but are onely a ſort of <hi>begottery,</hi> into which, Devotion, not well regulated, eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly degenerates. But you muſt not, under this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, laugh at all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſorts of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> which are to be proportioned to each capacity.</p>
               <p>I conclude as to this with St. <hi>Auguſtine, l.</hi> 12. <hi>de Civit. c.</hi> 15. treating of Angels: <hi>Vereor ne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius judicer affirmare quod neſcio, quam docere, quod ſcio.</hi> I had rather be
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:175639:73"/>not knowing, with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to holy Churches orders, than ſwell in a vain opinion of my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in prejudice of the leaſt of them. And this muſt be, except we would hear from the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, <hi>iviſtis in adin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventionibus veſtris:</hi> ye have left me, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in your own inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Chriſtian Religion doth not receiv eſtrength, by the weakneſſe of our reaſon, but our reaſon is elevated by the ſtrength of Chriſtian Religion. And therefore how ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent ſoever it is, it
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:175639:73"/>muſt vail bonet, if a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt be interjected.</p>
               <p>And therefore Maſter <hi>White</hi> in his <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-Logick,</hi> and his four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth reflection teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus, conſonant to <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Apollinarius</hi> their fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and falls: <hi>How mean &amp; pittiful a change it is, to fall from the ſplendid authority of the whole Church, to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure authority of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Doctor be he what he will.</hi> Surely it deſerves an Aegyptian Pyramid to perpetuate it againſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:175639:74"/>all innovations, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, againſt this which we have rejected.</p>
               <p>Yet there are a ſort of <hi>Opiniators,</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> calls them, who fancy each ſtrong fancy of theirs, to be <hi>demonſtrations:</hi> to which all, who will not incurre the note of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, muſt ſubſcribe, as well in <hi>Morals,</hi> as in queſtions, touching faith.</p>
               <p>Whereas St. <hi>Auguſtine, l.</hi> 1. <hi>Retract. c.</hi> 21. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting learnedly, and largely of the ſence of our Lords words to Saint <hi>Peter, ſuper hanc Petram, &amp;c.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:175639:74"/>thus: <hi>Harum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum ſententiarum, quaeſit probabilis, eligat lector.</hi> Antiquity then did not diſalow probable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: nor preſently fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy their own conceits to be <hi>demonſtrations;</hi> much leſſe forbid others to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch, which they judged <hi>probable.</hi> Which is now too much cryed down, and truly as to Morals, I conceive I have demonſtrated in my <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyridion Dial.</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability is enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:175639:75"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>The deſigne of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHereas you ſay, I dare not aſſert the contrary opinion of the <hi>ſouls</hi> continuing in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> till the day of judgement to be <hi>Hereſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is eaſily replyed, firſt with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that to preſcribe any term to particular perſons, and much more to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that is, to determine months, or yeares, <hi>non niſi temerè definiri poteſt,</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:175639:75"/>it is a great temerity; becauſe, as he ſaith ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly, it is <hi>resincertiſſima:</hi> there is nothing more uncertain in all Chriſtian principles. For indeed here is neither <hi>reaſon,</hi> nor <hi>revelation</hi> to conduct us. He ſpoke upon occaſion of <hi>Scotus</hi> his opinion, who thought, according to the meaſures he made of Gods <hi>mercies,</hi> that none would ſtay in Purgatory above ten years. Which weak ground brought <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen</hi> into his error, of promiſing a period to the pains of Hell. Thus great wits, ſtill produce by
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:175639:76"/>ſtrength of fancy, new grounds, and thence of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten new errors into the Church; but to aſſert a detayning all <hi>ſoules</hi> in <hi>Purgatory</hi> till <hi>doomeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> notwithſtanding the Churches <hi>Suffrages, Alms,</hi> and <hi>pious helps,</hi> is, for ought I can ſee, a <hi>novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and if ſo, it is eaſily proved to be a falſehood: for amongſt the ancient, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, were almoſt equal crimes, as accompanying each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>To what you demand further, it is eaſily rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:175639:76"/>example: <hi>Quis conſtituit me Judicem?</hi> I am no Judge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies. That is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to S. <hi>Peters chair.</hi> Therefore I dare not indeed preſumptuouſly cenſure other Catholike Doctors opinions, whoſe perſons, and learning I juſtly reverence. Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf therefore within the bounds of the Schooles, my deſign is onely to vindicate the <hi>Churches Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>conſtant practiſe</hi> (as I am able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it) from <hi>ignorance,</hi> and <hi>Novelty.</hi> In this
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:175639:77"/>none can juſtly blame me. Neither ought any to conceive themſelves to be particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it; the rather, becauſe I do not believe (when they ſpeak clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their long <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi>) that they intend any further, than in order to <hi>natural cauſes:</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of which, as the Souls are not capable to be changed, as you lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, and truly teach, after, and with Mr. <hi>White;</hi> ſo by force of ſuch, or by order of <hi>Nature,</hi> they cannot change their poſture from
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:175639:77"/>
                  <hi>Purgatory</hi> to Heaven: which is a great truth.</p>
               <p>If any will go further, I ſay with St, <hi>Paul: Non ſic didici Chriſtum:</hi> I muſt leave them: yet with St. <hi>Hieroms</hi> Proviſo, in his <hi>Dialogue</hi> againſt <hi>Pelagius, l.</hi> 3. <hi>In dogmatibus diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendis, non perſona, ſed cauſa quaerenda eſt.</hi> I touch no mans perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> teacheth his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, (treating St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians</hi> caſe) to be modeſt in their <hi>tenets,</hi> conceiving there may be venial ſin, in being too forward, or heady, even before Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical declarations, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations:
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:175639:78"/>and St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, Apol. l.</hi> 2. ſaith: <hi>Si quaeſtiones de animaeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe commotae ſunt, quae eſt iſta qucrimonia vel querela, quae utrùm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipi debeat, Epiſcoporum judicio derelinquitur?</hi> This muſt be decided by <hi>Biſhops:</hi> chiefly by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> as he teacheth againſt <hi>Ruffinus</hi> in the ſame <hi>Apology;</hi> and in his 67 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi> he ſaith notably: <hi>Scito nihil nobis eſſe anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quius, quàm Chriſti jura ſervare, nec patrum tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre terminos, ſemperque meminiſſe Romanam fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:175639:78"/>Apoſtolico ore lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam; cujus ſe eſſe partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pem Alexandrina Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia gloriatur:</hi> We muſt all glory to ſubmit to the deciſions of <hi>Rome,</hi> when Patriarckes themſelves are taught to do it. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording therefore to our friends deſire, I onely let him know, for prevention of miſtakes, what I have learned in <hi>Scotus,</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas</hi> their Schooles; and what was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our amicable Collation; in nothing (as I hope) violating the lawes of true Chriſtian <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> which I hold ſacred,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:175639:79"/>as being conſiſtent with that well meaſured Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: <hi>Amicus Plato, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus Ariſtoteles, magis amica VERITAS.</hi> Which method, as you know, was religiouſly obſerved by learned Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> in his ſharp con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſes with <hi>Tindal,</hi> when he objected his great friend <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his verſion (reduplicating in vain the notion of a <hi>friend</hi>) againſt the ſenſe of Holy Church.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
